Greetings everyone and welcome back. It
is great to have you here for the second
day of our generative AI intensive
course, a co uh collaboration between
Kaggle and the Gemini team. Um today
we're going to talk all about uh
embeddings and vector databases.
Hopefully you were excited to see all of
the great discussion that happened
yesterday around foundational models and
prompt engineering techniques. Uh and we
have a great kind of set of sessions
here today where we'll be walking
through some code labs. Um doing a Q&A
with some of the people who are building
these tools and features for Google. Uh
and then also a pop quiz at the end. So
make sure to pay attention. Uh this
5-day generative AI intensive course
which is sponsored by Kaggle and by the
Gemini team. um also includes a Discord
channel to discuss our live streams and
to engage with the guest speakers and
community and Q&A. Um so make sure to uh
to log in to ask your questions and they
might just be selected for a future day
um uh as you're reading your assignments
and and kind of learning more about all
of the great content. Um, be sure to
check out all of our collabs that you
can run online as Kaggle kernels. Um, as
well as, uh, engaging with some of the
white papers that we've been sharing.
Um, and as mentioned, this is day number
two, um, of our generative AI intensive
course. Hopefully, you've read uh, the
embeddings and vector databases paper.
Um, you've uh, explored some of the code
labs and a not. We'll be showing you
some of these coming up very soon. Um,
and you'll also be learning about the
conceptual underpinnings of embeddings
and vector databases and how they can be
used to bring um kind of specialist data
and and really exciting production
techniques into your large language
model apps. Um, so with that I am going
to go ahead and turn it over to Anant um
who is going to be walking through some
of the amazing kind of curriculum review
and code labs uh that we have planned
for day two. So Anant uh Anant take it
away.
Thanks. Thanks Paige. So uh welcome
everyone. So before I get started with
the code lab um just wanted to walk you
through some of the content that you
have read through in the white papers as
well as maybe the podcast if you had the
time to go through it. But uh so uh you
might have seen in the white paper that
uh it starts off with um exploring what
is embeddings and the different kinds of
embeddings. So in the realm of machine
learning we often grapple with different
diverse data types right text, images,
audio and more. And often many
applications can benefit from
representing these objects of different
data types in a comp compact fixed
numerical representation which captures
the semantic meaning and relationships
between them and that's essentially what
embeddings are in a nutshell. So we are
basically transforming complex data into
semantic numerical vectors that can be
used for downstream tasks. We also
looked at in the white paper that um
different types of embeddings text image
and multimmodal embeddings as well as
structured data and graph embeddings. Uh
and then we also dived into the various
algorithms and approaches that can be
used to create train and use these
embeddings as well as their
corresponding trade-offs. Now after that
uh once we have the embeddings uh in
order to use it for downstream
application it is important to have an
efficient way to search through uh say
hundreds of thousands of millions of
embeddings uh given a query and find the
most semantically similar one but do so
in a very time and costefficient manner.
And that's where uh approximate nearest
neighbor algorithms come into play. And
we looked at um how embeddings can like
the various metrics can be used to
compare embeddings to see like judge
similarity which embeddings are similar
to one another. Um so example if king is
similar to queen in the contextual sense
more than king is similar to a car then
that's something we can should be able
to compare and um find out and to do
this at scale uh approximate nearest
neighbor algorithms such as hierarchical
navigable uh small world as well as scan
um uh come into play which can help you
with this. Then after that we looked at
the various uh vector stores and vector
databases that can be used which
implement these approximate nearest
neighbor algorithms at scale and the
various operational considerations and
how to manage these uh in production.
Then after that we concluded the white
paper by looking at some of the
applications of embeddings for example
by using uh a pre-trend embedding
representation uh of various objects and
adding a small layer on top to benefit
from the rich representations and
leverage that instead of training from
scratch and use it for classification
tasks. We also looked at how embeddings
can be used for recommendation problems
as well as ranking problems and many
others. So uh having said that that's a
great segue to our collab in which I'll
be walking you through um some of these
let us get started.
So your first collab for um for this day
for day two was one where we built um
where you built a document Q&A system
using rag and chromadb. Now what is rack
right retrieval augmented generation it
has three parts and it addresses the
very important uh limitation of LLMs
which is that LLMs are often limited on
to the knowledge they're trained on and
often do not have access to the latest
dynamic information unless you provide
it using uh systems like these and even
if they do have access to certain
knowledge providing this uh the most
relevant information and latest
information in the in the prompt itself
can help improve uh the performance and
reduce hallucinations. So rack system
has three stages. The first one is
embedding and indexing the various
documents uh in the database as well as
embedding the query. And then the
retrieval stage uh comes afterwards
where you take the query uh embedding
and look at all the documents in your
database and say okay which ones are the
most similar documents the most relevant
documents that my LLM should have access
to um uh in order to give me the most
appropriate answer. and then the
generation part like provide this uh as
part of the prompt the most relevant um
context and documents and generate the
uh answer. So in this particular collab
we uh built a s uh simple toy um rag
system. Let's look at how we did that.
So we installed the necessary libraries
as we have done um in the previous
collabs as well. retrieve the API keys
um from the Kaggle secrets to call
Gemini API and then we uh explore the
various available models. Um so here um
we look at the embedding models
available so like the text embedding
models which we we will be using for the
rag system. Then we create a small toy
data set uh consisting of three
documents um which will be which we will
be using as our database for this uh
collab.
After that we create a function to take
a document and embed it using um the
embedding API. Um and in this case we
are using the text embedding 004
embedding API and uh we uh we make this
function which can be called um to embed
a given document.
Then once we have the data set defined
and the embedding a function defined, we
use uh uh we basically um initialize
Chroma DB Chroma database um and and uh
use this function and uh to add the
documents and it automatically embeds
them uh since we are uh we are
referencing the embedding function which
we defined above. So it's adding the
documents and indexing them uh in memory
and uh using the embedding function to
make sure it indexes the embedded
version of the documents not the raw
documents. Then we confirm that the
documents were indeed added to the um to
the uh vector DB. And then here we uh we
see if the semantic search with the with
the vector DB is actually working. So we
give a query and we query the database
and we find the most the most similar
result and that is seems to be correct
given the context of uh the three sample
documents we pro provided it and then we
use that um we use the retrieve result
as context to to an LLM here in this
section where we use it as uh uh we
expand the prompt using that sample um
retrieved uh document and we use it to
generate the answer. So congratulations
uh if you've reached here you've and
you've understood it you've built a
retrieval augmented generation app. Now
moving on to the second collab for the
day. Here we see uh how embeddings and
uh can be used um uh to understand
similarity between various documents. In
this case, we'll be working particularly
with text embeddings, but you can also
use multimodel embeddings.
So, similar startup uh with the Kaggle
secret um to retrieve the API key and
initialize Gemini. We also then kind of
explore the models which are available
to us for embeddings.
And then here is uh the important bit uh
which will help you understand here. We
define the various text documents,
sample text documents, uh, which we want
to compare with one another and find
okay for each one of the documents, how
similar is it like semantically from a
meaning perspective to the other
documents in this list. So which is what
we will be doing here. And so um we see
we do a semantic similarity um and map
the heat maps uh from each document to
every other document. So in this heat
map uh you see something very
interesting. So um so one the the
lighter shades refer to very high
similarity semantic similarity while
darker shades refer to lower semantic
similarity. And you can see that the
sentence the quick brown fox jumps over
the lazy dog is most similar well to
itself. You can see here this is the
most similar to itself and but uh uh but
it's least similar to uh documents which
are completely random like lortoum
etc. You can see that it kind of makes
sense that is it is the case right? U
and if it's uh if you look at the exact
similarity scores here, the document
this uh the quick brown fox jumps over
the lazy dog. It's most similar of
course to itself because it's the exact
same sentence, but it's second most
similar to just a slightly misspelled
version of the same document because the
meaning kind of still remains the same
just a given a small typo here. And then
you can see that it's third most similar
document also kind of implies the same
meaning and so on and so forth. And this
is kind of how you a human would also
rank it. And the semantic similarity is
captured very well using by embedding
these documents. You can use this for
various purposes such as clustering,
ranking, um retrieval systems etc.
Now
if you let's go on to the third code
lab. Now here's a slightly different use
case of embeddings. Uh the first two
talked about retrieval uh using semantic
similarity of documents. This one talks
about how you can use embeddings as a
rich representation
uh to to bootstrap your um uh further
downstream models and utilize this rich
representation as a very informative
source so that you do not need a lot of
data or very complex models uh and can
already leverage the information within
this embedding.
So in this collab um we would start off
with um using pre-chain embeddings that
can uh uh classify news that can help uh
help uh classify news group posts with a
small kas model added on top. The kas
model in question would not be trained
on raw text data from scratch but be
leveraging these embeddings as a source
and adding a couple of more layers on
top which can help uh greatly um be very
data efficient and uh learn the uh learn
how to classify the news group posts
into various categories.
So um we start off as usual with
initializing API and retrieving the API
key initializing Gemini with it and then
we look at the news group text data set
where we have a lot of news group posts
across several topics and uh our aim is
to make a model which can take the text
content of a news group post and
classify into one of the topics. Some of
them uh are mentioned here.
So I'll be skipping us this one. And
we'll be pre in this cell we pre-process
the news script posts to uh clean it a
bit. And then we make a train and test
split for the post. So uh we would like
to train it on the new script posts um
an existing class labels or the category
labels and then um learn how to predict
uh um class or target labels for un uh
for new news post where the um where the
class label is unknown and see how it
performs in the test set.
So um this is all pre pre-processing and
yeah so here's the the most important
bit creating the embeddings and using
that for a downstream model. So in this
case because we'll be performing a
classification task we would be let's
use the classification
task category for the embeddings you can
use various different categories um
depending on the task you're doing and
then we um we define functions to create
embeddings here and then um we create
the embeddings out of the training and
test data sets
and then um in this section we um add
couple of dense keras layers. So dense
layers using the create keras framework
and we will uh where we take the
embedded inputs and pass it through a
couple of uh layers and and then the
model learns how to classify this um to
the new respective news group target
categories. So keep in mind that here we
are not learning from scratch. We taking
the embeddings as a input. Hence the
model does not need much as much data
and it does not need as much depth and
complexity. And by doing so we see we
train the model here. Um
we're doing so we can see that um the
validation um u um accuracy is improving
quite quickly in just seven epochs even
with limited data. And um it manages to
achieve quite a good accuracy with very
little data because we started we
bootstrapped it with embedded
representations and not raw text. So
this is something which can really help
you if especially if you have limited
data and hopefully uh it was clear and
yeah thank you and off to you page.
Awesome. Thank you so much for walking
through those great notebooks. Uh and
thank you uh thank you to Mark McDonald
as well for for kind of creating them uh
for for making them available um and for
uh for giving students the ability to
kind of get in and to uh to to sort of
start understanding how embeddings and
vector databases work. Thank you also to
the open source teams behind Chroma and
be behind Caris. Um uh really excited to
see some of those tools used with the uh
used with the curriculum as well. Um, so
let me go back to our slide deck. Um,
and it looks like it's time to get
started with our Q&A. Um, so, uh, the
question and answer session is brought
to you for you by you. Um, all of the
great questions that you've been asking
in Discord, um, uh, will be used to kind
of, uh, uh, to kind of create questions
for our Q&A session. I also want to make
sure to thank our generative AI course
moderators Pong, Ca, Mark, Eric, Irwin,
and Miles who have been answering your
questions in real time on Discord and
also helping uh people get unstuck from
some of the things that might have been
a little bit challenging with some of
the assignments. Um so, please virtual
round of applause um for all of our
great course moderators. Um and a great
uh a great and warm welcome to all of
our expert hosts here for day two. We
have many folks from DeepMind as well as
from our our Google cloud AI teams um
Omid Alan um Shiaoi Jenhuk uh Yan
Eftakar and Anant. Um wonderful to have
you here today and thank you for taking
the time to answer questions for our
students. Um and with that I'm going to
go ahead and get started with our first
question. As a reminder, if you would
like for your questions to be answered,
make sure to add them in the Discord as
you're going through the course
assignments each day. So, first of all,
um for Alan and for Yan, tell me a
little bit about vector databases and
embeddings. What are they and why are
they useful?
Sure. Um I will start with um an
introduction of embeddings and then I'll
hand over to Alan to talk about vector
databases. So embeddings uh in numerical
vectors we use these uh embedding
models. Embedding models are machine
learned models that convert real world
objects such as text, image and video to
embeddings. And these models are trained
so that the geometric distance or the
similarity of the embeddings reflect the
real world similar similarity of the
object that they represent.
Embedding models can be used in
recommendation systems, semantic search,
classification,
rag, and many other applications.
Google's Vert.x AI platform offers
two classes of pre-trained embedding
models. text embedding models and
multimodal embedding models. Text
embedding models allows you to convert
plain text to embeddings while
multimodal ones they work with image,
audio and video input and in addition to
textual input.
So to use these models you simply enable
vertex AI in your GCP project and send
request to vertex endpoint. We also
support customizing these models your
using your own data set.
Vector database are storage solutions
that specialize in managing these
embedding vectors. Uh now I hand I'll
hand over to Alan to talk more about
those uh vector databases.
Thanks Yan. Uh my name is Alan. I'm part
of Google cloud databases and the lead
for alloy DB semantic search. And now
that we know vector embeddings capture
the semantic meaning of unstructured
data, vector search is the operation
that given a set of stored embeddings
and a query embedding finds the nearest
neighbors to that query. That is the
most similar items to that query. Vector
search can be done by computing the
distance between the query against every
stored embedding. And this is called
exact nearest neighbor search. But
imagine how slow this operation would be
if there are a billion stored vectors
that uh uh we need to compute the
distance for. So vector databases speed
up vector search through approximate
nearest neighbor search which gives
highly accurate but approximate answers
while doing orders of magnitude less
work. And there are a number of
approximate nearest neighbor algorithms
in the industry and they typically fall
into two broad categories. Graph-based
the most popular being HNSW and
treebase. And one stateofthe-art
treebased algorithm is Google scan
algorithm. And this is based on 12 plus
years of Google research and it's used
internally inside Google at Google scale
in products like Google search, YouTube
ads, photos and we've incorporated the
scan algorithm natively in multiple
Google cloud products including alloy
DB, cloud spanner or manage my SQL
bigquery and vertex vector search.
Awesome. So it sounds like uh embeddings
and vector databases are very quick ways
for you to understand how similar
certain kinds of data might be to one
another. Um and we have many different
managed service options um for
embeddings that are offered through
Google cloud also through the Gemini
developer APIs as well as you can uh
kind of use open-source tools like
Chroma uh and other vector databases in
order to to do the work and to store um
to store all of the embeddings that you
create for your projects. Um, awesome.
Thank you. Thank you so much. Uh, and
then next question. Um, what are the
tradeoffs? Uh, speaking of open source
vector DBs, um, what are the trade-offs
between using an open- source vector
database, um, versus a proprietary one
like some of the some of the managed
services that were just being mentioned
on on Google Cloud? Um, Omid, do you
want to do you want to go ahead and take
that question?
Yes, thank you. Uh, so, hi everyone. My
name is Omid and I'm part of um Google
Cloud's BigQuery where I lead the a IML
and search areas. So uh this is a great
question. So
I'd say the trade-offs are similar to
how the trade-offs are in other other
areas of technology. So to be more
specific, so the open-source vector
databases may be more favorable for uh
aspects such as cost, flexibility,
customizability, community support, and
also potentially avoiding vendor
locking. Um however, uh often times that
needs to be balanced with uh things such
as higher maintenance cost,
uh higher management costs and
complexity.
and potentials for fragmentation down
the road and along the way kind of
limited support options.
Now with the proprietary vector
databases is kind of the essentially the
flip side of that, right? So they often
have an edge in terms of ease of use as
a more managed service support and more
advanced features and stability.
But the downsides can be cost, potential
for vendor lock in in some cases and um
limited customization flexibility and
sometimes transparency.
Now um this being said, I would also
actually like to uh draw your attention
to the increasingly powerful uh vector
search and indexing capabilities
that are being added across various uh
general purpose databases.
and data analytics and warehouse
platforms and these are being added as
first class citizens as Alan mentioned.
So um you know basically and by the way
this is this spans both open-source and
proprietary proprietary worlds but you
know for example you know you can think
of the PG vector extensions for
Postgress and in the case of uh Google
cloud you know for um database and data
warehouses we have all spanner and
bigquery all of them adding very strong
capabilities as first class citizens. So
um now the advantage of looking into
this option is that you know they would
u help avoid data duplication across two
databases. So you'll have just one
database as source of truth and you'll
continue to benefit from decades of work
that have gone into building these
highly advanced capabilities into these
general purpose databases and data
warehouses. And essentially you use them
as a single source of truth and the you
know you you know you use the added AI
and vector capabilities which you know
keep growing very fast. So that's also
another option I wanted to bring up as
as part of the answer to this question.
Yeah. And that's that's amazing to hear
that instead of having for uh instead of
users having to figure out should I use
a vector database or should I use a more
traditional database um uh these these
kinds of features are being added uh and
cross-pollinated across both. So you
don't have to you don't have to have
data duplication and you don't have to
understand uh you know which kind of
tool or technique you should be using.
you can just kind of adopt those
features within things like Postgress
which most folks already have experience
using.
Very very cool.
Thank you. Uh that that's great to hear.
Um and then also uh so next question. Um
this is uh this is for Takar. Uh do you
think new features and capabilities like
Gemini's longer context windows which
are now up to 2 million tokens uh in
context and Google's recently released
search grounding will reduce the need
for vector databases or these uh or
these kind of features and and um tools
complimentary to each other.
Thank you Paige. Uh hi I'm from Google
Deep Mind and uh thank you for this
great question. uh I will start by
expanding the question and explaining a
little bit. So there are two new
technologies that are mentioned. One is
long context windows as Gemini and other
language models can support more and
more tokens as part of the input and the
other technology is search grounding
where we recently released the uh
capability to issue a web search and
ground any answer and validate if that
is correct or incorrect. So uh first
let's talk about the longer context
window. Of course, it's really exciting
that we can scale to much longer
context, but still uh we are not ready
to actually do that at a very large
scale for several reason. First, uh our
we currently support a few million
tokens, but most realistic databases or
corpus, they're much larger. We often
need billions or trillions of tokens.
Also, it's really computationally
expensive to do like um full run the
full LLM over a massive amount of
tokens. Whereas, as uh Yan and Alan
explained, vector DBs are extremely
efficient. So, they can retrieve from
bill billions of items very quickly. And
finally, we saw that as we put more and
more uh irrelevant content in the
context, then the LLM's reasoning
capability starts to degrade. So it's
often more useful for us to first use
the vector DB and retrieve the most
relevant documents or content and then
perform reasoning on thing which are
actually relevant to user question. So
in that way actually vector DBs are a
really exciting and uh complimentary
technique to the new long context uh
language model capabilities because now
the initial retrieval stage that doesn't
have to be uh extremely precise instead
we can focus on the recall retrieve lots
of relevant documents put that in
context and then LLM can reason over
that large amount of context and
absolutely I I I Just wanted to to say
really quickly that I love that uh I
love that pattern that you just
described of being able to use vector
databases and retrieval to figure out
what is the most effective information
that should go into the context window
in order to help support your outputs.
Um I think I think that's something
that's been underexplored to date and I
I really love that you called it out.
Yeah.
Yeah. I I'm super excited and also it's
helping us to think a bit differently.
In the past we would like have very
limited context. So we would focus too
much on the uh precision of the
retrieval whereas now we can be more
recall oriented because we can support
slightly more amount of tokens in the
context but then throw a larger net get
all the relevant content and then reason
over it. Uh there is another part of the
question about search grounding. I would
just very briefly mention that search
grounding allows us to ground uh to the
web or the all the public information
but often we want to do search or do
grounding on our private information
like our personal data or in a company's
proprietary private corpus and for that
we still need vector databases because
public search will not have access to
those private data.
Yeah, absolutely. And I and I know that
Google Cloud has uh has implemented a
feature that is um not just search
grounding but also grounding on
arbitrary data that might be hosted in
GCS. Um so so I think that I think that
you're right. You know there will always
be a place for both u you know retrieval
to get the most pertinent information
and then also the ability to to kind of
search um search over the web to to be
able to to find the the most recent
information.
Cool. Um so next question. What are the
fundamental challenges and opportunities
for vector databases? Alan, would you
like to take this one?
Sure. Thanks, Paige.
So, uh, speaking from the perspective of
building a vector search index natively
within an operational database. Um, so,
uh, from an operational database, uh,
customers perspective. Um uh this is a
system of record uh for these users
where they expect transactional
semantics, strong consistency, fast
transactional operations and data that
spans memory and disk. One interesting
challenge that uh we've uh been working
on has been how to achieve the same
performance of uh specialized vector
database systems that don't have these
same constraints. Uh, as one example of
an innovation, the AODB team has
implemented a custom underlying buffer
page format in order to leverage scans
low-level optimizations.
And other opportunities that I see that
apply to vector databases in general uh
are in the areas of improving usability
and performance when vector search is
only one part of the application logic.
Uh so for example uh vector search with
filtering is a well-known challenge
where it may be more efficient to do
post filtering or pre-filtering
operation uh depending on the filtering
condition and the user's intent is
clear. Return the nearest neighbors to
me that passes the filtering condition.
Um right now a lot of the systems uh uh
need the user to specify okay I want to
apply the filter after the vector search
or vice versa. Uh but uh the vector
search uh databases should be able to
automatically figure this out um uh
figure out the actual filtering
operation that will give the best
performance uh without the user needing
to specify that. And this extends out to
combining with other application logic
like joins, aggregation, and text
search.
I love I love what you just called out
about introducing these AI capabilities
into traditional databases and then also
improving the developer experience for
them. I think that that will bring um a
lot more capabilities to folks without
necessarily making folks learn how to
use uh use new tools or techniques. Um
and I'm really excited to see uh to see
what everybody builds as well as the the
new improvements that are coming into
products in in GCP and to open source
databases. So this is very very cool. Um
thank you for thank you for that great
answer.
Yeah.
And next question. So, so we've been
talking a lot about uh you know what
happens when everything goes right when
we're able to find the most relevant
documents or or kind of data assets uh
and then use them as part of our
projects either by uh by taking in the
information and using it with the
extended context windows or or by using
it directly within the databases. Um
what happens if uh retrieval uh uh if
retrieval augmented generation doesn't
retrieve your relevant documents or your
relevant data assets? What can you do?
Um and Shiaoi uh do you want to do you
want to start?
Oh yes. Uh thanks page.
Yep. So it's uh it's not uncommon that
uh rack systems when they retrieve the
document for specific query if the
document previously is not like embedded
in the corpus or the corpus doesn't have
relevant informations some irrelevant
documents may be retrieved as a top
neighbors for the query and uh so in
that case I think it's rely very heavily
on the like the backend larger models
factoriality capability
to understand whether the retrieve the
documents can or cannot answer the
question and there are like other
methodologies we can uh make sure like
the rack systems can can still
functional well when the nonrelevant
documents are retrieved so I will pass
and then to introduce about the agent
yes thank you Zaki so yes as mentioned
um it's um you can tune embeddings like
you can kind of make sure that the model
can understand and um the rag system
works well because when the search part
works well of rag the the retrieval then
um you can improve the generation as
well if the relevant documents are
improved. Um but uh what you can also do
is uh um uh make instead of just doing
uh simple rag system where you kind of
use embeddings and then vector databases
to find the most relevant set of
documents and then uh like five or 10 or
so such documents and then using those
documents in your prompt for generation.
You can use an agentic system uh where
you and uh an AI agent kind of figures
out okay based on the query and the
prompt uh it calls various it takes
various different steps. It can uh re
call vector databases different ones or
it can also um uh take different steps
such as use grounding services and
various different tools and techniques
in order to retrieve the most relevant
documents and then supply that. So
instead of a static process of go ahead
find me the top five most relevant
documents and feed that it figures it's
a dynamic process where it takes a steps
tools uses a bunch of tools and
technology and figures out how to uh how
to um provide the most relevant content
for the prompt. So we by the way um uh
uh on the next day day three we'll be
covering the topic of agents in in more
detail. So I'm super excited about this.
Excellent. So, it sounds like there are
many different there are many different
things that people can do in order to
kind of improve the likelihood of
getting the right answer, the most
relevant answers for um for their rag
approaches. Um so, this is great and I
am I'm sure that a lot of people are
excited about uh day number three's
content and getting to be hands-on with
creating their own agents and using them
to solve problems. Um so see
excited to talk about that tomorrow.
And then next question
um the mainstream of LLMs are decoder
models. Um how can we train an embedding
model from a decoder only model
backbone? Um Etakar do you want to take
this one as well?
Sure. Um yeah this question is a bit uh
technical but it's also very exciting
and interesting. Um so typically the
traditional large language models they
are decoder only and what we mean by
decoder only is that they are trained in
a way that the task is to predict always
the next word or the next token and the
model can only look at all those words
or tokens that came before it. So it
cannot look at ahead of the token like
say words that come after the token. So
this is like a unidirectional left to
right causal attention and this is very
efficient. Uh we can do lots of
optimization during training assuming
that this attention is just one
directional and we don't have to look
ahead and as a result this is being
adopted more and more for LLM training.
However, for encoder style task, for
example, if we want to create an
embedding for a piece of text, it's
actually helps us if we can have like
birectional attention. That means every
word can look at all the words that came
before it and all the words that came
after it. And for this actually if you
look at the state-of-the-art most recent
embedding models, they are all starts by
initializing from decoder only large
language models. But then they are
further adapted or more trained to learn
to do birectional attention that means
pay attention both to words before it
and the words after it and that improves
the embedding model quality. So in short
actually uh uh the state-of-the-art
embedding models do use birectional
attention something like encoder style
models but they are usually initialized
from the decoder only backs and then
some additional training happens to make
them really strong encoders.
Excellent. Thank you for that great
description. And uh and if folks want to
learn more about this where would be the
best places for them to go look? Do you
have any favorite papers or textbooks
that they could go that they could go to
learn more?
Uh I think of course there is the
classic paper about transformers that
explains the attention really well and
the BR paper which shows the advantage
of birectional attention of a
transformer-based encoders. uh but there
are also a few recent papers. One I can
mention uh from Nvidia uh where they
explain in depth how they are adopting
decoder only models for encoders but
there are many other similar work both
inside Google and externally.
Excellent. And we can make sure to add
those paper recommendations to the to
the YouTube video um for folks to be
able to to go and to take a look at. Um,
thank you for thank you for that great
discussion.
And then our final question before we
head into the pop quiz. So hopefully
everybody has been paying attention. Um,
uh, Junjuk, uh, after all of this
discussion, um, does this mean that
conventional methods for creating
embeddings will become obsolete? Um, you
know, I I think we were discussing a
little bit around, uh, kind of these
multimodal techniques. Um, do you have
any uh any perspective on whether
conventional methods um might need to
change or evolve based on all of the all
of the questions and all of the insights
that we've been discussing here today?
Yeah. Uh so my name is Gini. Uh so
there's a small typo. uh it's not you
but J I N but anyway uh I think the
conventional method uh if you're talking
about the OCR related technique where
you extract the text first from like a
PDF and then converting it to a like a
text embedding model uh I think uh
there's a good chance that ex uh the
future embedding models that recognizes
like text from from an image uh might be
able to capture that uh into advance
vector representations. uh but I think
the current status of the multimodal
embeddings are not accurate enough to uh
capture all the uh like the uh the exact
text in the image image. So I would say
uh for for maybe next year or so we
might need to uh combine both methods uh
to take the the advantages from the both
worlds.
Excellent. And I apologize for the typo.
Um uh if folks want to to learn more
about Jen Hook's research um
we will make sure to add um kind of a a
link to Google Scholar um as well uh in
the in the YouTube notes.
Awesome. And now um without further ado
um we are going into pop quiz territory.
Um, so the pop quiz is just uh five or
six questions after the end of every day
to kind of test your comprehension both
of the podcasts, the papers that you've
been reading, as well as the Q&A
discussion that we've had with all of
our uh all of our subject matter experts
here today. Um, so get out your pens,
your pencils, um, just something to
write down uh, write down your answers
and we'll be walking through each one of
the questions um, uh, in real time. So
uh so make sure to to get these uh to
get these questions um answered. First
off um what modalities can be converted
into embeddings? Um we discussed this a
little bit in the in the Q&A session and
you should have read a little bit about
it in the white papers as well. Um for
modalities that can be inverted uh
converted into embeddings um a image, b
video, c text or d all of the above. All
of the above could be turned into into
embeddings. Um, I'm going to give you a
few moments to to pick your answer and
count down. Five 4 3 2
1. Hopefully everybody picked D. All of
the above. Um, you know, as we were
discussing before, we can have texton
embeddings, but we can also have
multimodal embeddings that encompass
image, video, text, audio, uh, kind of
all of the modalities that you can think
of. Um, so, uh, so definitely explore
embeddings not just for text, but also
for other use cases.
Question number two, um, which of the
following is a major advantage of scan
over other approximate nearest neighbors
search algorithms? We discussed this a
little bit in the Q&A, especially uh
during the the questions to Alan and
Tion about uh about vector DBs and and
databases. Um so so uh get out your pens
and your pencils uh and think about the
think about the best answer. Um number A
is uh it is open source and widely
available. B it is designed for
highdimensional data and has excellent
speed accuracy tradeoffs. C, scan only
returns exact matches, or D, it is based
on a simple hashing technique and has
low computational overhead. Which is the
best answer? Um, and again, I'm going to
do a countdown backwards from five. Five
4 3 2 1. Hopefully everybody picked B.
Um, scan is designed for highdimensional
data and has excellent speed accuracy
trade-offs. That's part of the reason
why um we care so deeply about it at
Google um because we we need to care
about things being fast and being
scalable. Um so uh so hopefully
everybody got the question number two
correct. Um number three, what are some
of the major weaknesses of bag of words
models for generating document
embeddings? Um this hopefully you you
got to see a little bit in the white
paper as well as maybe in some of the
code labs. Um but uh value A they ignore
word ordering and semantic meetings. B
they are computationally expensive and
require large amounts of data. C they
can't be used for semantic search or
topic discovery. Or D they're only
effective for short documents and fail
to capture long range dependencies. What
are some of the major weaknesses um of
bag of words models? Um, I feel like I
should have Jeopardy music, but five,
uh, four, three, two, one. Hopefully
everybody picked a They ignore word
ordering and semantic meanings. Um, then
next question. Which of the following is
a common challenge when using embeddings
for search and how can it be uh how can
it be addressed? Um, is it that
embeddings cannot handle large data sets
and you should use a smaller data set in
order to address it? Is it that
embeddings are always superior to
traditional search and there's no need
to address that challenge? Um, is it
that embeddings might not capture
literal information? Well, um, in which
case you need to augment and combine
with full text search or is it that
embeddings change too frequently and so
you should just try to prevent updates?
Um, which of the following is the is the
correct answer? Um, think about it in
five, four, three, two, and one. Um,
it's that embeddings might not capture
literal information very well. Um, and
so if you do use it and combine it with
full text search, um, like some of the
techniques that we were discussing
today, um, then you will be able to get
much more accurate results and and
hopefully be able to build stronger and
more robust systems. And then final
question
um what is the primary advantage of
using locality sensitive hashing for
vector search? Um is it that a it
guarantees finding the exact nearest
neighbors? B that it reduces the search
space by grouping similar items into
hash buckets. C is it that the only
method that works for highdimensional
vectors? Or D is it that it always
provides the best trade-off between
speed and accuracy? What is the primary
advantage of using locality sensitive
hashing? Um hopefully everybody was
paying attention in the white papers. Um
and five 4 3 2 1. Um and it is that it
reduces the search space by grouping
similar items into hash buckets. Um so
as I mentioned everybody make sure that
you uh you write down your prep quiz.
Um, if you missed a question, make sure
to review uh and to refer back to those
items in the code labs and in the white
papers. Um, uh, and also make sure for
tomorrow uh, to add all of your great
questions in the Discord about agents
um, so that perhaps our our subject
matter experts can answer them um,
answer them in real time. Um, so thank
you again so much for attending uh,
attending the second day of the
generative AI intensive course. I want
to give a big round of applause to all
of our uh to all of our subject matter
experts for answering the questions, for
coming today um and for sharing their
knowledge. Um and uh we'll see you back
bright and early um or uh uh whatever
your your time zone might be um for day
number three where we we'll be
discussing agents. Um so all the best
and uh and thank you for participating.